Hey what's up guys? My name is Ashar,
and welcome back to my C++ series. So
today we're going to be talking a little
bit more about memory, and specifically
how we can track allocation and
deallocation of memory. Now the thing
about memory is that it's important. I'm
going to keep talking about memory
probably forever because that's how
computers work. Computers are very very
closely tied in with memory. If you just
have a CPU and you don't have any RAM,
you don't have any memory, then nothing
really is going to happen. And because
it's such a popular topic for
discussion, a lot of people sometimes
have the wrong idea about memory. And I
think that this is further complicated
by the fact that it's 2020. We don't
really have that big of an issue with
memory like we did 20 years ago. We have
gigabytes and gigabytes of memory. I
have like 32 gigabytes in my computer.
Most laptops come with like 8 or 16
gigabytes of memory.
It's kind of difficult to write a C++
program that's going to use that amount
or more. I mean not that difficult and
definitely depends on what you're doing,
but it's still
Hello world is not going to use too much
memory. So anyway, my point with all of
this is that sometimes it's useful to
know when your program allocates memory,
specifically on the heap of course is
what we're talking about. If you know
where your program allocates memory, you
can potentially work to reduce it,
therefore potentially optimizing your
program and making it run faster because
allocating memory on the heap is is not
the best thing to do, especially in
performance critical code. On top of
that, being able to see where memory is
being allocated can also help you
discover a little bit more about how
your program works. Even if you wrote
all of the code that you're currently
running, and we just like forget about
the C++ standard library, let's just say
it's all of your code, looking over a
large project that you may have been
working on for a while and being able to
see, okay, you know, my program
allocates memory here. I forgot about
that. Or that was something that was
from a long time ago. That's useful
information, and we're going to talk
about how we can see exactly where each
allocation comes from, as well as track
the overall usage of memory inside our
application by just writing the code to
do that, not relying on any other tools
whatsoever. And I also want to thank
Skillshare for sponsoring this video.
For those of you who don't know what
Skillshare is, Skillshare is an online
learning community for creatives where
millions come together to take the next
step in their creative journey.
Skillshare offers thousands of inspiring
classes for creative and curious people
on topics including illustration,
design, photography, video, freelancing,
and more. They've got tons of stuff on
their platform to help you learn a new
skill, and one of my favorite features
about Skillshare is that their videos
are quite concise, which means that I
can fit them into my schedule, and I
have time to actually use them to learn
something new. A lot of their
illustration classes I particularly like
because I'm always interested in
improving my art, and they also have
plenty of classes to get you started on
how to make videos. Make 2020 a year in
which you explore new skills, deepen
existing passions, and get lost in
creativity with Skillshare's online
classes. And with an annual subscription
of less than $10 a month, Skillshare is
a great way to do all of that. And the
best part is that Skillshare is offering
the first 500 people who sign up using
the link in the description below two
free months of Skillshare Premium. So,
go ahead and do that as soon as
possible, and thank you as always to
Skillshare for sponsoring this video. I
also want to thank all of you for
subscribing and watching my videos
because we've hit 200,000 subscribers on
the channel, which is quite a cool
milestone. What I thought I would do for
that is do a bit of a Q&A.
I have not done a Q&A video in like
5 years, probably. So, if you guys have
questions for me, then drop them in the
comment section below. I'll be looking
at the comments of this video to see
what I should include in the Q&A.
Please don't ask me to fix your code.
Now, let's dive into some code and take
a look at how exactly you can be more
aware of where you're allocating memory.
So, here we have a completely blank C++
program. I'm going to use this as the
foundation for showing you guys all of
this stuff. Keep in mind though that in
general, everything I'm going to show
you here today, you can easily plug into
an existing application of yours. That's
kind of the way that I'm intending for
it to happen. Maybe in the future we'll
take a look at this inside a real
project, but for now I'm just going to
strip back all of that kind of craft,
all of that extra stuff that isn't
really relevant at all. And we're going
to take a look at the core basics. The
first thing I'm going to do here is
write a little object because this is
probably going to be a good example of a
real world use case. I might have an
object, let's just say it contains int
xyz. We have three integers in here.
Now, if I create it on the stack, I'll
probably end up with something like
this. However, if I create this on the
heap by calling new object, then of
course that will result in a heap
allocation. And the point of this video
today is how can we detect things like
this? The way we're going to do that is
by overriding the new operator and
specifically we're overriding this
operator globally. So, to do that we'll
type in void pointer operator new and
then size_t size. So, what this is is
the new operator. This new keyword here
is actually a function that gets called
with a particular size and potentially
other arguments as well. By writing this
code here, we're saying do not use the
operator new that is in the standard
library, use this one instead. The
linker will actually link in this
function instead. Now, of course it's
good to actually allocate memory here
because that's the point of this. Your
program probably won't work if you
don't. Of course, you could retrieve the
memory from anywhere. The point of this
function is to return a void pointer
which is just a memory address. So,
because we don't really want to affect
the behavior of our program, we'll
simply type in return malloc size. So,
what this will do is allocate the
appropriate amount of memory for us and
return a pointer to that memory. So,
with this change being the only change
that I've made, if we run this normally,
nothing will change, but this new
keyword will now run through this
function, which is quite nice because I
could easily type in something like
allocating
size
bytes, for example. And now it will
actually print that to the console. And
perhaps the other benefit to simply
writing something like this is that I
can now easily stick a breakpoint here.
And if I run this program, you'll see
that my program breaks on this line. And
I can look at the call stack, and I can
see that, "Oh, okay, it's coming from
this line of code." Now, of course, in
this case, that's super obvious. But
what if we made something like a string?
So, let's just say we have a string
called "Cherno". Now, this is a small
string, so it won't allocate memory on
the heap to store these characters.
However, we are in debug mode, so we
still will allocate some memory. If we
launch this now, you can see that this
allocation is coming from this line of
code, and we can actually track that all
the way in the call stack through
string, and see that, "Okay,
we call operator new here, and we
allocate eight bytes of memory, which is
also, you can see, what our console
reflects." Just in case it's not 100%
clear, I also want to point out that
this does not just affect you explicitly
calling new. If you use smart pointers,
so for example, if this was a unique
pointer,
and then let's change this to make
unique with
object. I'll just include memory up
here.
Then, obviously, memory will still get
allocated here. If I run this code,
we'll skip past the string here to the
next allocation, and you can see that
this happens from within make unique
because unique actually, of course,
creates the object on the heap by
calling new. So, hopefully, you can
already see how useful this is. You can
stick a breakpoint inside that operator
new function, and trace back exactly
where those memory allocations are
coming from. Another really good example
where this is super useful is if you're
working on a game engine or a game, when
the game's actually running, when you're
rendering frames, like let's just say
you finished loading, you finished
initialization, all of that, you're in
your level, you're just playing your
game,
frame to frame, you want to minimize the
number of allocations you have because
they that can have a quite significant
performance impact. So, what you can do,
and what I have done in the past, is you
can just stick a breakpoint inside that
operator new function while your game
loop is actually running and kind of
trace exactly where those memory
allocations are coming from frame to
frame. And to be honest, a lot of them
are probably going to be like string
operations and stuff like that, but
sometimes you can you could make smarter
decisions. For example, maybe you have a
vector that keeps getting a resize,
maybe you can define that size ahead of
time or use something that doesn't quite
allocate as much memory. Or maybe you
can write a memory arena or something
like that for a given uh system or
operation or something in your game loop
so that you can reduce actual memory
allocations that keep hitting the heap.
It's all seriously useful stuff. If we
go back to this little example of ours,
we can also write the matching delete
operator, which just looks like this. We
have operator delete and then a pointer
to the memory that we want to delete.
Now, what we can do here is just type in
free memory and that's really all there
is to it. Now, if we put a breakpoint
here and we maybe take this unique
pointer and put it into a little scope
here, what you should see is this
operator delete being called from this
main function after this unique pointer
is destroyed. And you can see that it's
the actual destructor of this unique
pointer here that is actually deleting
our underlying raw pointer. Now, if we
go back here, you'll notice that this of
course doesn't actually contain
information about the size, so we can't
really print anything like this. Well, I
mean, we can. We just have to add that
parameter in because at the core, this
delete operator doesn't really need size
information, but you can optionally
obtain that information by just
overriding this specific function
signature. So now if we take a look at
this and we just let our program run
naturally, making sure that I actually
write something like freeing, you can
see that now we allocate 12 bytes, we
free 12 bytes, we allocate another 8
bytes, and we free 8 bytes. So now using
these two functions, we can create some
sort of allocation tracker. We can
maintain allocation metrics. We can find
out exactly how much memory is being
used, how much is being allocated, how
much is being freed, all of that stuff,
which of course becomes really useful.
So what I'll do is I'll come up here and
I'll write a struct called allocation
metrics. This will contain a uint32_t,
which will be our total allocated
memory, as well as our total freed
memory. I'll also write a little
function here that tells us our current
usage.
And this will just be total allocated
minus total freed. I'll create a little
static instance of this struct here, and
then instead of printing this whole
allocation thing, I'll just say
s_allocation_metrics.total_allocated
and then I'll do the same thing for the
delete operator, but of course that'll
be our total freed. So now what I can do
is maybe write a function called print
usage.
Call it print memory usage so it's more
clear, and this will simply output our
memory usage.
Which will be
s_allocation_metrics.current_usage
bytes.
Okay, cool. So now I can print my memory
usage at the start. I can print it after
allocating this object. I might move
this string up to make it a little bit
more interesting, and I'll just I'll
just put these everywhere. Let's just
run this program. So now you can see
that at the beginning we're not using
any memory, then we've allocated 8 bytes
for this actual string. Then we've
allocated another 12 bytes for these
three integers, because we have three
integers, 3 * 4 is 12. And then finally
we're back down to 8 bytes after this
scope ends because we freed our unique
pointer. Pretty cool stuff. Anyway, if
you guys found this helpful, go ahead
and throw this into your own programs
and actually test it out and see it in
action. I do want to make a note that of
course you could use tools for this. You
don't have to write code that does this
yourself. You could use Visual Studio's
built-in kind of memory allocation
tracking profiling tools, whatever
they're called. Valgrind also has some
nice tools for tracking memory and
seeing where it's coming from like
allocations coming from, all of that
kind of stuff. So, there are tools
available out there and I might make
some videos on them in the future, but
for me personally, this is a very quick
and dirty way to actually see what is
actually going on and also trace it back
within your code without having to kind
of use other tools. They they are
definitely useful and I'm not saying
that you shouldn't use them. All I'm
saying is that sometimes it's just a lot
easier and more simple to just write
something like this and instantly be
able to see exactly where those
allocations are coming from. And this is
definitely something that I use in my
own technology all the time. And in
fact, in a bigger kind of game engine
for example, you would probably have
your own kind of operate new operate
delete, all of that stuff because I
aside from having to just track metrics
and make sure that works across all
platforms, you also may want to control
exactly where that memory is coming
from. Anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed
this video. If you did, please hit that
like button. Don't forget to leave any
questions that you may have for me in
the comment section below for that 200k
special Q&A video and I will see you
next time. Goodbye.